good evening good evening and welcome i call to order this meeting of council for tuesday march 25th 2025 uh one point of order uh administration bill number two 2025 which is listed on the agenda later this evening for its first reading uh would not be presented today um and for all those able
and willing please stand for the pledge of allegiance mr harris mr harris can you please
call the roll of members yes mr. vice-president mr. man here mr.
Arroyo here mr. Glees here miss Craig miss Diaz here mr. Hirsch here and
president Baker council president bakey has excused this excuse this evening a few friendly reminders plea note please note this meeting is being live streamed and recorded if you are making a public comment this evening please do so at the microphone and state your name and address for the meeting record also please be sure to silence any cell phones and devices first I'll hear a motion for the approval of the March 11th 2025 meeting minutes motion to
approve second the motion in a second mr. Harris mr. man I mr. Roya I mr. Glees I miss Greg yes mr. Hirsch I next we'll hear any proclamations honors
awards and resolutions of recognition mr. Harris do we have any we do the
first is council resolution number 21 2025 the resolution of the council the city of Lancaster designated March 2025 as Women's History Month in the city of
Lancaster Pennsylvania motion to approve second we have a motion in a second this resolution was brought forward by council president bake a honoring Women's History Month any open it up for any council comments any comments from
the public miss Ayers mr. men hi mr. Roya hi mr. Glees hi miss Craig miss
Diaz hi mr. Hirsch I will move into our first public comment period this is reserved for citizens who have contacted the city clerk prior to the meeting to request the opportunity to address City Council the duration of comments are limited to three minutes. Mr. Harris, do we have any? Yes, we do. First this evening is Ahmed Zaki.
Please make sure the green light is on the microphone. Hello, good evening, City Council member and Ms. Mayor. My name is Ahmed Zaki, 336 Beaver Street, Lancaster, PA. A lot of people know our story. I think we no need to repeat it again. I'm here again for the third time to talk about justice unfortunately there is no justice when we post on our facebook page about our problems some people recommend us to go to city council and address your problem city council and we got some feedback or some help from this two member of the city council personal help unfortunately it was not useful and we we expected from city council as the people recommend us that maybe they could help us give recommend us to the court or help us with the public defender unfortunately nobody was scared about this even 50 percent of our problem caused by City, Lancaster City Inspection Department, but nobody was scared. And we all, we all, and at the end of the things everybody, I think, bowed to the flag and at the end of the song was justice. That always take me my attention, justice, when I'm hearing the justice and I think I find I got allergic for the name of the justice, because there's no justice. I, we, I am as a citizen when I soar to to this country. I followed the law. I paid everything. I never did anything wrong. But officially, nobody followed the law. I think by barking or crying, nothing will change. It is already written in modern slavery book. There is no justice for the poor people. If there is something or if everything is a scam, a circle of scam on the court that turning you around, again you're coming back to money i should teach my kids and everybody should teach that they be they should be careful how system working here and who the right who is right who's wrong is not a problem who is the richer who have money they are the winner and we cannot make american great again some people say again all right now anytime without justice justice is the greatest greatness for everything with the justice. A country cannot be country. A father cannot be a father. A society cannot be a society if there is no justice. That's all. I think I have to keep silent and sit in my place. And I think I cannot do anything more of this. What I did, I did it for three times in a year. After this, I have to keep my problem in my heart and sit with myself. Thank you so much.
Our next speaker is Maura Humble.
Hi. My name is Maura Condon Humble, and I live at 231 North Shippen Street. Thank you all for giving me a few minutes. Six and a half years ago, I lost my son to firearm suicide. And over the last couple of years, to try to deal with my grief and loss, I decided to get involved with Moms Demand Action for Gun Sense and Ceasefire Pennsylvania. I learned there, I learned with these organizations, that most gun deaths in this country are suicides. That shocked me. Most gun deaths in this country are suicides. I assume that might be shocking to a lot of people. Ceasefire Pennsylvania and Moms Demand Action are dedicated to reducing or hopefully eliminating gun violence of all kinds, including suicide. So I'm here tonight to encourage all members of city council and all city leaders and anybody else who's interested that's here tonight to attend a cease-fire Pennsylvania panel discussion on this Thursday night at 630. It's being hosted by Benchmark Program, which perhaps you're familiar with that wonderful program, a very impactful community violence intervention program on South Prince Street. We'd be so grateful. I would be so grateful for as many of you as possible. Some of you have actually already RSVP'd, and I'm so grateful for that. I'd be so delighted. We'd all be so delighted to see as many of you and the mayor as well if you are available. And as I said, it's open to anybody who's interested. I have a QR code with the registration information about the details and RSVP information here.
Thank you. Next speaker is Daryl Legace.
Hi, my name is Daryl Legace. I live in the 100 block of North Mary. Thank you so much for letting me speak here tonight. I was going to come and speak about the use of force incident from almost a month ago now, but I think other people are going to do a better job of that. instead I'm going to talk about the council and the future of the council. So there's very likely that next year there's potentially a vacancy on the city council, right? If one of the two city councillors who are running for mayor win, there'll be a vacancy. The last time there was a vacancy, you all asked for applicants and you chose somebody. And so I hope you do that again if there ends up being a vacancy. And if you do, I'm going to apply. But here's the thing, I hope you don't pick me. I live in the southern end of Chestnut Hill, right? Not the rich, fancy area, but still, Chestnut Hill. If I go out my front door and lean a little bit, I can actually see the mayor's house, or at least your front door. My area doesn't need more money or more investment, right? There are lots of parts of the city that need it. So instead, I hope you pick somebody who's working class. I hope you pick somebody who makes under, say, $50,000 a year. I hope you pick somebody who's paycheck to paycheck in the southwest or maybe in the southeast. I hope you pick a parent and here's the radical part pick a renter There's no reason you cannot according to the regulations pick someone who rents in the city I think that would make a huge difference So here's the other thing. I know that the council has certain powers and certain things They can't do you can't fire the police chief. You can't suspend the officers You can't demand that officers walk a beat But what you can do and I hope you will is you can call out the chief when he's wrong And you can call it the mayor when I think the mayor is wrong you can do it here at city council you make proclamations you can do it personally you can do it in the newspaper you can go to protests you can lead protests you can march with us and i think we need to see more of that it's not going to help your political advancement like if you do that you're probably not going to become mayor or state representative or state senator but here's the thing it's the right thing to do you have a chance here to change things right and i think and hope that you're spending let's say one term changing things here and then you go back and go to your old job instead of staying on the council for terms and terms and terms and not changing things this is your chance to change the lives of people that live in this city and there's a lot of things that i think you can do and i think one of them is standing up and
being more vocal so i hope you do mr harris next speaker next speaker is john mayna good evening
everyone I'm John Mina of 24 West Main Street Strasburg Pennsylvania I'm sick and tired of being sick and tired that's what Fannie Lou Hamer said to the world in 1964 and tonight during women's history month we honor her legacy by telling the truth we too are sick and tired sick and tired of the same cycle a video goes viral community members express outrage and the police respond with a statement that tells us nothing except that once again the public is wrong and the department is right but this time lancaster showed up two weeks ago residents partners and yes members of this very council agreed that what happened on march 2nd is not what community policing should look like and yet we've been here before this being the third incident as many months where force was used instead of de-escalation. Instead of transparency, we get a press conference that blamed the kids, that blamed the parents, and the community, all while protecting the system that failed it. We don't need more excuses. We need action. And that is why we submitted our resolution two weeks ago. We asked for an independent review of the March 2nd incident, not one led by the department itself. the department can't police itself that's why we demanded it public release of all past and future use of force reports we want to track patterns and hold systems accountable clarity around the role and authority of the public safety committee and last but certainly not least establishing a civilian review board so the people have a seat at the table where their safety is being decided let's be clear this is not just about one incident or one officer this is about trust trust that has been broken but it can be rebuilt if courage is shown now courage means facing the hard truths about our systems it means not retreating in the bureaucracy or hiding behind internal reviews it means standing up and saying we will not accept this as normal we are not here to attack you we are here because we believe Lancaster can do better and we know you believe that too but belief without action is complicity so tonight we ask for more than words we ask for partnership policy and political will to stand with the people who elected you as dr martin luther as excuse me as dr martin luther king jr once said there comes a time when one must take a position that is neither safe nor politic nor popular but he must take it because his conscience tells them it is right that time is now thank you next speaker is abby haney hi thank you my name
is abby haney i live on the 600 block of east madison street and today i come to you as co-chair of the lancaster democratic socialists of america the press conference held by chief mendez and mayor srachi on march 18th was nothing more than an attempt to deflect blame from the police department onto literally anyone else the kids in the city their families and the community it was also a tacit endorsement of the treatment of these children and what they received regardless of prior interactions that they had with the police there was no excuse for the force that was used on them this was and will continue to be a failure of the Lancaster Police Department to de-escalate frankly it was disgusting that these kids were characterized as criminals and that the insinuation for the use of force was that they could have been carrying guns the issue of juvenile gun control Lancaster had absolutely nothing to do with the situation it was yet another instance of deflecting blame onto anyone but the officers involved the statement spoke of the ways your department is involved in the Lancaster community sure it's great that one of your officers plays basketball once a week with kids but that doesn't build trust what officers can be hired from outside of Lancaster City to come into our community to police black and brown people there that's automatically an imbalance of power and it seems clear to us why there's a lack of trust and respect and escape the commute and to scapegoat the community to accuse them of not showing up for their kids is disingenuous Lancaster is home to diverse community organizations that serve our youth finally to give yourselves a pat on the back about your accreditation and in your statement with a call for folks to join the police department if they want to say in public safety was tone deaf and out of touch instead of using more taxpayer dollars on expanding policing why doesn't the city establish a Public Safety Commission or a civilian review board where members of this community have the agency to hold our police department accountable. Surely, a good faith demonstration of trust would include community oversight. Our demands as a collective of organizations remain resolute. Number one, an update on the status of an independent review process. We cannot trust the police to investigate themselves impartially. Number two, a public commitment to making all past and future use of force reports available to residents, not just quarterly. And three, to establish a public safety commission or have a plan in place for Civilian Review Board. These demands are not radical. They are a step towards the transparency and accountability that members of this very council called for at the last City Council meeting. Should they be unwilling to compromise, it sends a message that the city and its governing bodies are unwilling to prioritize resident safety. Lancaster DSA is calling on you to have the moral courage and fortitude to follow through on these demands. We refuse to have our children, please, this way. Thank you.
Mr. Harris, next speaker. Next speaker is Jackie Snyder. Next speaker is Megan Keller. And the next is Susie Gomez.
Susie Gomez, 100 block of North Reservoir Street. I'm going to hand you guys a document.
Okay, so you have in front of you a page from the newspaper article where Amanda, Izzy, and Xavier, and Jamie were also in a riot at the protest. Here, uh it was told to this council that they were to create um a commission for blacks and browns affairs can you since amanda's not here jamie tell me what happened to that 2020 policy that
you guys had pushed are you done with your public comment i'm sorry are you done with
your public comment am i done with my public comment that's a question sir yes are you refusing to answer no I'm not done with my public comment I'm asking a question are you refusing to answer there was a policy that was pushed in 2020 and miss vacay had asked council to do the same exact thing and what you see in front of you is a draft that Lancaster can adapt or adopt since nothing happened in 2020 here's a draft that Janet gave me from Harrisburg City Council but we all know that nothing will happen because you block her on everything and you can't even answer a question now when you were involved in this protest you guys fought to put in place a Commission Board to hold these officers accountable
what I'm asking you is a simple question what happened yeah I think I'm done with
my public comment because it goes to show that you don't even have an answer it goes to show that you know you're in question also
those protests. Mr. Harris any other speakers? Next speaker is Jontell Tolan. Good evening.
Jontell Tolan, first and only block of Wise Ave. I'm not sure if the Lancaster City Police Department is aware of this but the excuses they have given claiming videos show only part of the story labeling these children as juveniles to criminalize them and attempting to shift the narrative are not having the effect they think they should. These are children and I do not care what they have done their treatment at the hands of police was unjustifiable i am certain if this had happened in lititz or even here within city borders and our current department if these were average white children from lititz the response would have been vastly different that is the point the excessive force used especially on minors was not justified in an era where state sanctioned violence and suppression are becoming alarmingly alarmingly normalized the swift response from the community is more than warranted it is our right to challenge the rights of your own constituents to demand that we accept violence against our children without pushback speaks volumes about who you are and what you truly represent you must ask yourselves which side of history do you stand on the press conference held by chief mendez and mayor sirachi was not an attempt at accountability it was a deflection distraction and an insult to the people demanding real answers instead of transparency they chose to place blame on the children their families and the broader Lancaster community completely ignoring the fact that it was the police who escalated this situation they justified the unjustifiable blaming the people you are supposed to serve does not erase the failure of your leadership the refusal the refusal to release the body camera footage the dismissal of public concern and the unwillingness to engage with the actual demands of this community proved that the administration does not value the voices of those seeking justice instead working to build trust you offer bare minimum lip service instead of listening to the people you retreat into the empty statements and excuses but let me make something clear this community is not letting up we are not going anywhere if there is no trust there will be constant calls for accountability if there is no justice there will be a constant chorus of voices demanding change if there is no action there will be continued pressure confrontation and resistance at every turn we will not be pacified we will not be silenced Let me be absolutely clear about what is happening here. This is not just about one incident. This is about a long pattern of abuse, a long pattern of black and brown residents being brutalized, a long pattern of police being given free reign to harm without consequence. This is about accountability, not just for what happened on March 2nd, but for the policing practices that have allowed to keep happening. So let me make this even clearer. We will not stop until justice is served. We will not stop until these demands are met. We will not stop until real systemic change is made. If you think we will forget, if you think we will grow tired and move on, you are mistaken. The people of Lancaster are watching the history. It's recording how you choose to respond. This moment is defining. The question is, will you act with integrity or accountability? Or will you allow the city's leadership to be defined by deflection, distraction, and dishonesty? And that is why Lancaster organizations alongside this community are making demands the city has a choice either meet these demands or be prepared for the relentless unwavering pushback we are not here to ask politely we are not here to wait until the outrage dies down and officials in power hope we forget we are here to demand real structural change and here's what that looks like an independent review of the incident completely outside of legacy city police department their word alone is not enough their internal review already cleared the officers involved we do not trust a system that investigates itself what do you take us for public access to past and present use of force records uh reports transparency is not optional if you have nothing to hide then release the records let the community see the truth a civilian review board with actual power why is there no permanent independent oversight of policing a public safety commission is not a radical idea it is a necessity immediate action against our officer happy on the other officers involved we call for death duty within 48 hours we call for the changes against these youth to be dropped and yet no action has been taken that is unacceptable let me be clear this does not end here they can hold press conferences they can spin their narratives they can pretend they are doing their jobs but as long as they refuse to be accountable the city will be filled with voices demanding change you do not get to use excessive force and expect the people to be silent you do not get to betray your constituents and then act surprised when we push back history is watching lincoln will be remembered for what he choose to do at this moment and we will make damn sure they know the people are not backing down we are not asking for we are asking for change we are we are not asking for change we are demanding it and we will not stop until we see it happen thank you
thank you mr harris i'll close out the initial public comment period as a reminder there will will be one at the conclusion of this meeting or the end of the legislative agenda. Next is reports requested by Council. Mr. Harris? We have none tonight. Thank you. Next, we have interim reports of committees of Council. We have none of those either. Thank you, Mr. Harris. We'll move into our legislative agenda. First, we'll begin with the Ordinance of, excuse me, Administration Bill 12025. An ordinance
authorizing the occurrence non-electoral debt of the city of lancaster lancaster county pennsylvania by issuance of forty one million nine hundred uh sorry forty one million ninety five thousand dollars uh principal amount general obligation bonds series of 2025 issued for the purpose of providing funds for one general municipal projects including upgrades and improvements to the city's wastewater collection and treatment facilities for the city's water treatment and distribution facilities the city's parks and related facilities the streets and traffic signals within the city and related facilities each has set forth an exhibit a attached year two and other capital projects of the city as determined by the city two capitalizing interest on the bonds and three paying the cost of issuing and ensuring the bonds determined to sell the series of 2025 bonds the 2025 bonds at a private sale by invitation approving the form of the series of 2025 bonds fixing the number date interest and maturities of the 2025 bonds making a covenant for the payment of the debt service on the 2025 bonds pledging the full faith credit and taxing power of this city in support of such bonds, providing for the filing of required documents, providing for the appointment of a sinking fund depository for the 2025 bonds, and authorizing execution, sale, and delivery thereof, and other necessary action.
Motion to approve.
Mr. Harris, I would also like to make a motion to amend the bill.
Can you turn up the volume? It's very hard to hear. We cannot hear.
sorry mr. Harris please forgive me should I go ahead and read the motion to amend at this time yes thank you the motion for the motion to amend bond council has provided each of us with a black line version of the ordinance authorizing directing issuance of the general obligation bonds series of 2025 in an original principal amount equal to forty one million ninety five forty one million ninety five thousand dollars such ordinance was introduced as administrative bill number one twenty twenty five before this council on March 11 2025 I hereby move to amend the ordinance labeled administration bill number one 2025 to include the additions deletions and other changes changes referenced on such blank black lined version of the ordinance which will be reworded with the minutes of this meeting and which can be summarized as follows in the third line of the caption deleting dollar sign blank and replacing it with forty one million ninety five thousand dollars in the third whereas clauses deleting dollar sign blank and replacing it with forty one million ninety five thousand dollars inserting into the fifth whereas clause the name Robert W bar and company incorporated as the purchaser in the sixth whereas clauses deleting dollar sign blank and replacing it with forty one million eight hundred sixty three thousand one hundred and six dollars in section one of the ordinance deleting dollar sign blank and replacing it with $41,095,000 as the amount of indebtedness authorized by the ordinance. In section two of the ordinance, deleting dollar sign blank and replacing it with $41,095,000 as the aggregate principal amount of general obligation bonds series of 2025 authorized by the ordinance. In section nine of the ordinance, inserting the optional redemption provisions of the bonds as the bonds which are stated to mature one after November 1 2025 are subject to redemption prior to maturity at the option of the city in whole or in part on November 1 2034 or any date thereafter on exhibit C attaching the amortization schedule as provided by the purchaser a copy of the proposal of the purchaser has been attached to the ordinance as exhibit D. That is the motion. We have a motion and a second. And I will invite Director Campbell to give us an explanation on play level issues.
Thank you. So this is the second reading for the ordinance for the 2025 general obligation bond. Daryl is handing out some information that he will discuss in just a minute but as you've heard from the lengthy motion the amounts have been finalized based on the bond auction which happened today and the and the final costs we discussed the project list and amounts in detail at the Finance Committee on March 3rd so we won't get into that tonight but before Daryl comes to talk about the the final numbers I did want to just share a note on our bond rating with so with each proposed bond financing Moody's is our bond rater and they do an extensive review of our financial information to determine if an update of our bond rating is warranted last summer so in 2024 Moody's moved us from an a3 rating with a negative outlook to an a3 rating with a stable outlook and in review for this current bond financing at the beginning of March Moody's has moved this to an a3 rating with a positive outlook which is great news they saw the adoption of home rules a very positive move for the city as well as small increases in recent years to our emergency fund balances this rating plays a key role in many things but including directly affecting the interest rate for the bonds that we receive them by bond financing so I did want to just note that and on that note I'm gonna ask Daryl to come and talk about the numbers Thank You miss Campbell
good evening members mayor and members of council with that introduction I'm just really going to update you on discussion we had during the Finance Committee on March the 3rd miss Campbell already indicated that we went through the rating process we also put together an official statement or official statement it's a lot of information kind of good background on the city economic demographic financial information that's been provided to mr. Harris and I believe it's been been provided to you as well electronically so you know if you're looking for something to review it's certainly some good information about the city this is really what's used to essentially market the bonds so we wanted to get that to you for your review Tina shared the great news that the city's bond rating was affirmed at A3 and that you were given a positive outlook sounds just like it sounds positive out meaning the city has a positive outlook from a financial perspective so since we we met on at the Finance Committee again we've been working through that process to bring these bonds to market you had your first reading on March 11th and today as I think you're aware we have a bond auction to basically bid out your bonds to really all underwriters really from coast to coast to really bid it out and know that we're getting you the best rates available in the market today so we did that today but from 12 to 12 15 in this handout on page one is the summary we ultimately got two bidders to bid on your bonds they submitted four bids throughout those 15 minutes it's important to talk even though we have two bidders some of these bidders particularly Robert Baird works with a number of firms there's actually 25 firms in their so-called syndicate so you're really even though you see it okay it's two bidders it's really more bidders who are actually actually engaged in purchasing your bonds you know you go through this competitive process to again get you the best rate available at the end of the day Robert Baird the highlighted came in at the best interest rate of four point seven four two a lot more decimal points the other bidder was Wells Fargo the their best next bid was four point eight five percent they actually improved their bid throughout the process by point oh eight percent to put those numbers in perspective the difference between the four point seven four percent and the four point eight five percent is about eight hundred eighty thousand dollars in interest expense so actually looking at the best bid and the first if you call worse bid you know that was about point two percent so that's one point five million dollars so again why you go through this process with that I'll flip forward to the next couple of pages which again are pretty much consistent with what you saw at the Finance committee meeting I can certainly go over these in the detail but suffice it to say that the when we focused during the Finance Committee meeting essentially with doing these borrowings to provide eight nineteen million dollars for general fund projects ten million ten point three million dollars for sewer projects and nine point one million dollars for water projects for a grand total of a little under thirty eight and a half million dollars even know we're doing one bond issue they really have three specific and concise components to fund the projects for those three funds the general fund again the sewer fund and the water fund really the numbers are about the same as we talked about so I don't know I'll hit the highlights here so the general fund we didn't want to have any debt service impact in the current year because of course you've already adopted your budget so when you look at the existing debt service numbers of seven and a half million dollars for general fund ultimately you're gonna have about a nine hundred thousand dollar increase in 2027 and that'll be the total impact as resulting from these bonds really good the graphs I think a lot of you like the graphs better than numbers looking over to sewer fund to provide the ten point four million dollars for sewer projects you know you're starting at existing debt service of about four four point seven million in 2026 next year because of an increase is already happening the total increase in sewer fund debt service is going to be about a hundred and fifty thousand dollars and that's the full impact over the next three years the water fund for the nine point one million dollars of projects the existing debt services about 14 million dollars a year that service was already going to go up I'm gonna stress this already going to go up the green the green highlighted number in 2026 by about a million dollars it will go up another almost million dollars $985,000 again in 2028 that's really the impact of this borrowing so even though you look at it and say okay by 2028 water fund debt service by $2 million. Again, a million of that was already going to happen because of a previous borrowing. So again, the incremental or additional impact is about $985,000 from this borrowing to provide the $14 million. So those, again, are the numbers. Again, they're pretty much spot on of what you saw during the Finance Committee meeting. The next pages are all the numbers we just talked about in a graphical presentation. I think what this shows best is how there will be step-downs or reduction in debt service in outward years to either provide budget flexibility going forward or should you need to borrow additional money in the future, again, is that budget flexibility for additional borrowings. So page three is the general fund, the red lines being the existing annual debt service and the green lines being the resulting debt service after you do this financing. So, again, converting the numbers I talked about on the first page, in 2028, your existing debt service is going to go up about $900,000, but after three years, it's actually going to drop than $1.1 million in 2030. Then you can see it'll drop again in 2035 by another $1.4 million, and this financing is being done over a 20-year term. All of these terms, when I say that this is financed over a period of 20 years, it's to match the useful life of the project. Obviously it's appropriate that you finance the projects for not more than the useful life of the projects. Think of it like your car. You don't finance your car for 10 years when you know you're going to need a new one five years from now. The next page is the sewer fund. This is to provide the $10.3 million of projects. We're going to do this over a 30-year term. Obviously the projects being done for the sewer fund are much longer life, so again it's appropriate to do it over a 30-year term there in 2026 you have the increase of about $150,000 out in 2035 you're the one the green line goes down your debt service going around about nine hundred and thirty thousand dollars and then again in 2043 it'll go down another five hundred thousand dollars and lastly in 2049 or about 2.2 million dollars so again should you need to borrow in the future or otherwise you know you have that budgetary capacity or those reductions in your existing debt service we'll talk about the gold bars that that is one thing that's slightly different from when we're at finance miss Campbell and I'll talk about that lastly on page five same type of presentation for the water fund the red bars again being the existing annual debt service and the red bars being I'm sorry the green bar is being after the 2025 bonds if you recall from our page one that service is going to go up already in 2026 by about 1.1 million and go up another million dollars from this borrowing in 2028 and you can see it'll stay there roughly for the next 25 20 I'm sorry about 23 years this term of this component is a term of 25 years again to match relatively match the useful life the gold bars is not part of this bond issue but this is what we talked about when we were at Finance Committee meeting there is an anticipation that with the water transmission line you're probably going to be looking at a borrowing hopefully with pen vests of about 41 million the Gold bars are we'll just layering that on top again. It's just forward-looking that is not what you're approving this evening But you know and kind of the concept of looking forward and transparency Those are what you're expected to be looking at with the water transmission line project coming so that's really where we stopped with the discussion of finance committee the numbers numerically on the first page and the graphical presentations everything else behind this is really all the numbers and when I say all the numbers is a lot of numbers I'm happy to go over each one of these if you'd like but really they're just the numbers behind the graphical presentations page six is the source and uses again the bond issue will be 41 million ninety five thousand and that'll provide the thirty eight and a half million dollars of for the projects I'll just highlight them page 7 is the general fund component of the new bonds layering over the existing debt service page 8 is the sewer fund component page 9 is the water project component and then page 10 really just brings all three components together it's really the entire bond issue while we want to show you that again really you got to look at this almost as if you're doing three borrowings in one again to economize on on the related costs in the process so with that I'll certainly entertain any questions you've already introduced the ordinance the ordinance among other things would accept the bid or the proposal from RW Baird your bond counsel Ron Lord is here from Saxon stump and certainly if there's any questions on the ordinance uh she would entertain those but uh with that i will pause and see if there's any questions or else you can move forward with your vote i just want to share a little bit more
about the sewer graph i know daryl had mentioned that we would talk a little bit about that so he had mentioned that during the the finance committee meeting on march 3rd we had talked about the water fund having a penvest loan and overlaying with that as we had some further discussions with the public works department after that meeting we decided to do the same thing with some funding that we're going to need from for the sewer fund likely at the it will likely come at the beginning of 2026 but we wanted to just show that in the in the graph as well so that's what the yellow bars are it's about 9.7 million that we're anticipating would need to come from penvest so again it's not as part of the bond for this evening but that's that's that and it's it's three different projects nobody from Public Works could be here this evening so I will read the projects but if you have more detailed questions about those I will I will have to get back to you one of them is a new clarifier these are all for the wastewater facilities one is some emergency work on our chlorination facilities and the other is to improve our screening handlings in um the south train that we have thank you both and we had a pretty
thorough uh presentation during the finance committee um thank you both for the for the explanation um any council comments councillor med thank you mr vice president uh just one
question um and mainly just regarding the general fund projects uh it says that the dated date is 4 29 is that when the funds will be available to the city or when will these funds be available to the city after the passage of the ordinance uh yes your your assessment is absolutely
correct uh should you move forward and authorize this this evening uh we would close on april the 29th and you'd have the funds available for your projects thank you and this is a question probably
for director campbell uh given that the 429 date is when the funds will be available when will we see the schedule of the projects uh start to happen and will council have to re um well we have to re-vote on those uh ordinances or will the city keep us abreast of one of these projects some of these projects you know such as the welcome center renovations the the lighting bollards replacing that central market the um the improvements to ann and juniata i mean some of these projects are the community is waiting for so why don't we be able to know to tell them
this tab yeah we can come back with reports we don't need a new ordinances when the projects start so it would be a reporting out but we can we can definitely do that and i'll just add i think
the microphones do sound low tonight um i'll just add that uh in june council will be uh presented with a capital plan that is the um uh looks out over the next 35 years but there will also obviously be shorter term projects that will be on that and there are time frames for delivering those projects because we also need to make sure that we are um spending bond funds uh in an appropriate time period so that council will have a look at all of the capital projects that are projected moving forward in june and so that would be a great time to ask those questions counselor men and also regularly um you chair the public works committee no john uh regularly ask your committee uh leads uh for updates and projects that represent those areas
i thank you and i look forward to those updates thank you counselor oh there we go any other
council comments any questions from the public darling bird south hand street number one first i asked if i could get a copy of what you gave number two we have this new um council chambers we have that up there this isn't my first time saying this it would be very good for the public if what you're looking at could be displayed so we can also see what you were looking at as far as the report that he presented to you so we can get a better understanding of what he's talking about and i think i've asked this several times that if council is given of information that that is also displayed for the public so that we can see i think my question is about the projects not coming out until june i am very concerned that we're borrowing the money now and council's not really aware of a timeline of projects i think uh even during the home rule we asked for a five-year capital campaigns that would be going out i don't think there's enough information that i heard receiving about what projects we're spending this is a 41 million 965 is that what i heard 41 million 95 000 95 000 that they're asking for i know they said that the projects come to 38 is that correct 38 million and some dollars maybe an explanation on what the extra $3 million is where that's going would be helpful. I would like to know what council thinks. How's that going to affect the taxpayers that were borrowing this money? We did hear that the bond rate was good. I was glad to hear that the city was in a positive mood. I'm really glad to hear that. I think council needs to be able to explain to the taxpayer, what does this really mean to us? I mean, you're sitting there and you're making those decisions. We already heard that our water bill is going to go up 14%. How does borrowing this money affect that? And how are we expecting to pay that? We're looking over 30 years of bond, which a lot of you will not be sitting on council. Probably a lot of us will not be sitting in the audience at that time. But I think there needs to be a more clear explanation to the public in what we're doing here. Thank you.
Thank you, Ms. Burton. Just one point of reference. We did receive a presentation when this was initially introduced regarding the projects that this will fund from the general fund, water fund, as well as sewer fund. Also, the debt service was included in the projections when we were doing forecasting and when we passed the 2025 budget, just for some clarification.
Any additional public comment? One more for our city council and the finance committee here. I'm sorry, Mr. Maynard.
If you could just say your name and address.
Of course, John Mina, 24 West Main Street, Strasburg, Pennsylvania. When you guys were getting underwriters for the bidding process, did counsel or the finance committee kind of check or do their due diligence with any of these banks and if they're scaling back their DEI policies or anything like that? You know, with how the country is weaving away from some of those important issues, we want to make sure that we're not paying out banks that are kind of going away from what's important to the city. So is that something you guys did from a due diligence standpoint looking at who's coming to the table with their bids? And if they're stepping away because a lot of major institutions and banks Have kind of scaled away or cowardly backed away from DEI So I'm just asking if that's something you guys that are taking in consideration at that
Yeah, there's a there's a process that goes through the bond auction we don't typically review the policies for for banks and it's typically
required for us to go to the lowest interest rate that's presented that's yeah and just for my curiosity if council ever did want to know about specific policies that any financial institution does bid on is there a way
for us to find that information out yeah i mean yeah we could look at the bank policies but we don't typically do that in the bond auction so and i can also just say that much of our
investments are are with banks are through the pension boards and the pension boards are not controlled by council or even myself although i serve as president of the pension boards they They are made up of retirees and active employees who are focused on their retirement funds and the returns. We have had conversations regarding these issues in the past, and there's a lot of people on the Pension Board who have a lot of different points of view about this.
Thank you for the clarification. Any additional questions or comments from the public?
OK, Susie, do I have to say it again? Yes, please. Susie Gomez, North 100 block of North Reservoir Street. So while you guys are looking at projective reports and planning for your futures ahead, and a home rule is basically a positive view in the city because taxpayers are the only ones that are going to be burdened with this bond. There's grants that come up, you know, projects you have mentioned, Ahmad, projects for Ann Street and Juniata. We know that those projects were already paid for. Izzy secured a $500,000 grant for those projects. And then January 20 of 24, there was a construction company that came with a presentation to us at the school in Washington and shared that they were already paid $450,000 on that project. So what you were mentioning has nothing to do with this bond that they're discussing as far as projects are concerned for Southeast. The other thing is I just want to mention that as you continue to burden us as taxpayers in the city to look at a bond that is going to be secured for the next 25, 30 years that our children would have to pay for. because as the mayor mentioned she's already on the president board she has her future plans and it's well established that's why you guys ignore us because it's not what we want there's no common interest here there's no commonwealth there's just socialism in this administration it goes back and forth we know that 9.1 million dollars was given to the water system for a grant along with the seven million dollars you know i mean there's money pouring in from grants there's other means of grants that can be established so that we can pay a debt not go more further into debt and deprive the people especially our children while you secure
your futures shameful any additional questions or comments from the public excuse me patrick
I just want to say it's embarrassing the political sleight of hand you pulled when that gentleman asked about which banks and financial institutions you're collaborating with. These are institutions that cause untold suffering across the world that are collaborating with our fascist government in Washington, and you just ignore it. just brush it away as if it doesn't matter thank you my name is Brian Nelson
I got a little too close here sorry so my name is Brian Nelson I live off of Columbia Avenue I'm right outside Lancaster City and so I completely understand kind of your guys's point when you're talking about you know the bonds and stuff like that but did you guys do any due diligence at all and I understand the bank thing too but I do hope that you guys do consider in the future actually looking into who you're doing business with I think that that would be a good practice so maybe that's something you guys can look at in the future but in terms of like the bonds and stuff did you guys do any due diligence to find out if there were any other sources of funding for these projects or did you just jump straight into let's get a loan so I just want to know kind of what that process looked like for you guys and did you figure out could we get a grant could we you know maybe use some federal funding what options did we have before we burden our citizens with third with like 31 or sorry 40 whatever it was millions of dollars of debt that gets paid onto the taxpayer no we're paying you so i mean i would hope you guys can figure that out yeah happy to add some context
specifically whenever these projects come i know the administration works very hard on the team at
city hall works very hard to find other funding opportunities many of our projects are grant
funded a good example which i think was mentioned earlier with the ann and juniata streetscape project, we did receive $450,000 in the Crystal Communities Grant, but that still leaves $950,000 unfunded, which will be funded by the bond. So this administration, I know, does work hard to look for other funding sources to try to alleviate some of the pressure on the taxpayer, but good question. Anything that I'm missing, Director Campbell, with that? I think you mentioned most
of it. I would just say that many of the projects in the project list do have grant funding associated with them but they often require some sort of batch and so that's what's the what's listed in the projects and I'll just add one more thing to that
which is that we are under significant and I'll be talking a little bit about this in my remarks regulatory pressures in which we need to meet certain milestones to address water quality and other issues please also recognize that that our water and sewer systems serve customers in and outside of the city and that when we borrow funds there are a variety of ways to finance and and that usually is borrowing through bonds through going out to banks and getting a low bid and or using the state revolving loan program that is operated through pen vest is another option so the borrowing for the size of projects is a significant infrastructure project so one that we're working on right now is a 42-inch main replacement that is running 13 miles from the susquehanna river into the city that's approximately it's on the verge of probably 100 million dollars between design and construction costs as well as material costs just to give you scope of the size and scope of projects that we're talking about so I'm also particularly proud that we have 70 80 million dollars of grant fundings under grant funding under management and I will also just say that I expect us to not have that opportunity because federal grants are drying up any
additional questions or comments from the public I just wanted to say that I
believe that I understand the bonds and I understand for the water and everything but I think when we talk about these other projects of parks and everything to actual get a bond to be able to you know do these parks we have come up with a better solution we're talking about 25 years you know how many times are the parks going to be redone how many times has the millburn park been done since you were on council let's just take the eight years and i mean to say this for 25 years i do and i agree with what's happening with the water in the sewer but i think these other projects we do not need to be getting a bond to do these projects because that's on taxpayers and there's got to be other ways to finance them and I think that should be taken in consideration we're talking about how much money we're trying to borrow now
bill Mr. Matthews aye Mr. Rowe aye Mr. Flicks aye Mr. Kerr aye Mr. Tietz nay Mr. Hirsh aye
we'll move on to resolution number administration resolution number 18 2025
a resolution to council of the city of Lancaster authorizing the disposal of certain obsolete records in conformity with the retention and disposition schedule for records Pennsylvania municipalities we
have a motion in a second councillor Diaz yes Lancaster introduced a
resolution number 18 2025 to authorize a disposal of certain obsolete police records this action aligns with retention and disposition of schedule of records for Pennsylvania municipalities as outlined in the municipal records manual the city has previously committed to the following schedule through resolution 7 back in 1975 the resolution allows police bureau records to supervise the disposal of specific outdated records insurance compliance with state guidelines for municipal records and management and for those that don't know it's basically citations like traffic non-traffic records from 20 to 21 animal compliance basically incident reports records from 21 to 22 abandoned vehicles incident reports records from 2018 to 22 permits and related application handicap application records from 2018 to 2021 noting that these application expired December the 31st and let's see oh let's see it was issued 2021 application expired on december 31st 2021 and that is it thank you councillor diaz
any questions or comments from council from the public jessica lopez lancaster city um i i don't believe that at a time where we're asking for transparency from our police department and and getting gaslighting and getting lied to and not giving evidentiary support to the things we're asking, we should be throwing away police records. I don't think that we can trust you enough to tell us exactly what you're throwing away. And I believe that this issue is out of touch right now and should be tabled until the impeding issue is actually taken care of y'all shouldn't be throwing nothing out in that police station right now how are we supposed to trust you when you literally just heard everything that went down in here week after week and want to sit up there and be like we should throw stuff away if i clean my house right before a raid they're going to be digging in my trash looking for the evidence what where's the disconnect here i didn't even know this was on the agenda but like where's the disconnect here do you not live around here i know for a fact some of you do what do you not see our kids go to school together you live on the same blocks you're drinking the same water what are you not getting about the issues and why do we think that laughing in our faces and promoting things like this is okay y'all didn't sit down and be like they're They're going to not trust us to do this right now? Anybody?
Mr. President.
I will say that this was tabled at the last meeting, given the discussion we were having at the last meeting. I thought it was most appropriate to wait until Chief Mendez or the mayor was available to answer any questions. The mayor is here this evening, so that's why I moved to bring it back on the agenda tonight, because we do have the ability to get the questions answered.
I appreciate that, Councilor Emmett. Now, so then the question is, where's the real list of what you'll be getting rid of? And how do you really prove that that's what you are getting rid of? We don't have transparency from our police department. We can't go in there whenever we please. That's a fact. It's not a public space. So you can just do whatever you want, throw away whatever you want, and we're just supposed to trust and believe this. feel like I don't know who else stands with me on this one it needs to be
tabled again my comment on that I second that this is an extremely tone-deaf thing to put forward to us at this moment in time I think it's disgusting that we would even could talk about it I hope that each and every single one of you votes nay because this is the kind of thing that you know we talked about a public review board and this is the kind of thing that a public review board should be looking at not the police force not you guys us because it's ridiculous that you know we keep talking about these issues with police violence and police violence all over the country and yet you are here talking about what 21 22 that's only three years ago that's not long enough they've been commit they've been doing police violence for the past few for like decades I don't want those records gone I want each and every single one of them held accountable for what they've done this is like each and every single one of you needs to vote no just flat out i don't even want a table i want it gone i want a public review commission they're the ones that should be making these decisions not the police not us i don't trust the police force they've shown over the over their last statements we cannot trust them why do you think i would trust them to throw something in the shredder i can't i can't even trust them with the evidence that they gather from somebody's home let alone the evidence that's sitting right in their own halls so I'm sorry I'm just flustered right now because it's baffling I I came here because I saw this on the agenda I saw it and this is why I'm here because this is ridiculous and you guys need to vote no or I hope that each and every single one of you gets a challenge for your seat I don't think that you deserve a seat on that council if you vote for this so again
this council creates Commission of black and brown affairs related to police brutality this was related to police brutality you're telling me that in 2020 you had established this Commission why are we here then why are we here are you lying to us Jamie now in regards to these records being thrown away we all know that these little citations and everything wants to make you guys look better so that your citation can disappear so that is a citation can disappear so that Amanda Bay case citation can disappear there's a lot more to this picture we're not idiots okay so just like Jessica said why should we not table it doesn't make sense your records can go away but we
can't get justice crazy counselor Diaz would you like to reiterate the explanation around the resolution and what it entails and disposing or what Records is disposing of just for clarity for the public for clarity as Jessica
said we would need to speak to the mayor because she is the one that authorizes
what the police are going to do so I'm happy to speak to this this resolution to destroy safety records as councillor Diaz walked through our first citation animal complaints abandoned vehicles permits and related applications it is the purview of council to make a determination about whether or not these records are disposed of i would also say that this is in keeping with policies and practices that are used per the municipal records manual which governs all of the municipalities across pennsylvania i also understand that um that there is a feeling in the room that this feels like why are you talking about destroying records um at this particular moment i understand and i hear that i would also say that this is a pretty regular thing that happens we bring it to council as a matter of transparency and in i mean in ensuring that we are following the municipal records manual this recommendation is submitted by the record supervisor who is a civilian staff member at the police bureau and council may decide what they would like to do related to this resolution we have we have these records they're there from five to eight years ago and you can decide what
happens to them thank you mary sorachi if i'm a mayor is there a right to know which i doubt because it's a pennsylvania law for the community to look at those records which i'm not sure if
that's possible i'm not sure either if somebody wants to see these records um they could submit a right to know request to review the records uh that would need to go through the right to know process and that's available to anyone in the room or beyond thank you can i report to that
um again i reiterate there was a et cetera at the end of that other related records so other related records could really be anything and at a pivotal time where we're looking for our future mayor to take a stand you have a position to say no we don't trust it and until you find a way to make us feel comfortable we have a 76.8 million dollar police budget those records have a place to be stored we pay for it hold on to them build trust in your community and then figure out out what to do with the paperwork later that's my suggestion on that because i recently watched somebody go through the right to know process and they were denied the body cam footage they asked for and forced into a 30-day extension because you don't want to give up the body cam footage we can't trust the police department and the right to know act isn't in place to protect us either
so who is youth say no it's that easy if i may um counselor counselor i think that what the community is talking about is that they do want a citizen's law enforcement advisory committee and by putting by placing that this is going to give everybody the opportunity to look at records like that and i did bring this up to several people in the community i forget the young lady's name but also to Susie and I spoke directly to City Council members that I know in Harrisburg if I mean if the community wants to hold on it let's vote let's vote on it but I think this is something that I could make a motion on at a later date for review for the bill of 98 2020 from Harrisburg to see if it's something that could fit the community and of course the solicitor and the the mayor will have to look at it as well.
Councilor Diaz, just for clarification, we are discussing resolution number 18-2025. That is correct. Not another, we're not introducing another bill at this moment? No, not at this point. Any others, Mr. President?
Councilor Bennett? When I made the motion to table this resolution at our last meeting, it was under the impression that we were going to have a report requested by council, and since it is not this evening, we're hoping that it will be the april legislative agenda i will make a motion to table this resolution until that report second
we have a motion to table the resolution did i hear you correctly to the next committee meeting
councilman uh yes to the april legislative agenda so that would be at the april committee meeting
to be reintroduced introduced and we have a second any questions comments on the motion to table
public comment starting bird did you say you're waiting on a report and you're hoping you have that report by the april meeting i didn't quite understand that uh yes the last meeting of the
council i made a motion to table this resolution that was passed unanimously i made that motion into thinking that the report that was requested would happen this evening and given that the community has requested to table it further i will make that motion to table until the april legislative agenda and we hope to have a report from the public safety
committee and chief mendez at that committee and if the report's not given you would not bring it
forward is that correct we would read this and i'll just add that uh it is it was my understanding that the report to council by chief mendez was for the april committee meeting and chief mendez
will be here for that meeting thank you i really appreciate that and i just want to second uh the bill number 8 2020 to be adopted and looked at by council respectfully i'm just reiterating that you
guys each have it any additional public comment mr harris on the motion to clarify this until the on the april 8th meeting correct and we will revisit it at that time thank you just a minute
that concludes our legislative agenda this evening um next we'll move into our second public comment period uh this is open for comment about issues not on the agenda uh duration of comments are limited to three minutes jessica lopez lancaster city um and this
of course is about what we all really came here for so let me start by saying i echo the members of the community that are already approached and spoke today but trust and believe we expected the reaction that we got at that press conference we expected them to gaslight we expected them to lie and our community still waited we did not harass use in the process we waited for that footage to only be denied for use for the police department to hide under the fact that there was juveniles in the videos so then I asked if it's because of the juveniles in the videos why were the parents denied the footage if it's to protect the children in the videos why deny the parents the body cams why make them wait a whole nother month to find out what really happened to their children that night this is disgusting this is disgusting like and I mean it in all serious it's not an exaggeration when I say it my kids are two times bigger than those boys and they're 15 and 16 if your cops are scared of those boys they're gonna be terrified of my sons and I promise you it's not a threat should that ever be one of my sons I'm not coming to City Council with my issue and that's the real problem that's where things are gonna get people can't trust our members to take care of this situation right now to allow that to attach those kids to guns the way they did and criminalize them the way they did and be like oh let's get upset because we put in so much work in our police department if you take out your trash this week you still have to take it out next week new people come new problems arise and you still have to handle them. In 2020, a situation transpired in downtown Lancaster. The city rioted, right? And you needed somebody to blame. I went to jail for 10 months so you could tell people to stop throwing frozen water bottles at your police station. And guess what? Nobody did it since. If you don't penalize the officers that are doing this, those other officers that are learning underneath them are going to think it's okay to do this stop saying oh we can't put him on administrative duties you can't no you can't fire him but you can keep him inside his cage and all of yous know that this is not whether it's through federal lawsuit or through things y'all done hush-touched and cleaned up
Hatfield's been an issue it's not new it's not new these are 20 year plus
senior officers that were taught racist policing ways and are embedded in them this is conditioning we all know about racist conditioning so as you continue to perpetuate this cycle and capitalize on us instead of protecting us and I have to say use because user who I talk to and until y'all change this it's gonna keep doing this this policing for profit that's going on around here why use bleed us for all our tax dollars what do you think you're gonna have left again you can't fire him fine keep him inside the building and stop saying you can't do that because you can use make the ordinances so y'all made the ordinance with the that the bike reflector issue came from use oversee the mayor who oversees the chief of police who oversees the officers you can tell him keep your job we'll continue to pay you sit at this desk is that is that
against the the so that's against the agreement we have with the Union yeah but
the mayor just said something so I was trying to hear what she was saying so yes that's against what the union contract is what i would say is that a lot of the things that are
being discussed there are real limitations and we are talking past each other and so i hear what the demands are there has not been a conversation that's been had outside of this chambers and i'm not sure that anything that i say tonight is going to be helpful to this audience at this
moment it's not about what you say it's about what you do that's the thing it's not about what you're talking about or what I'm talking about it's about what
you do there are limitations on the council's there's a limitation there's
a lot of limitations there there is so is it a facade and we have City Council members and a mayor that's supposed to oversee a department that really
oversees itself it is clear that we need to have a better and a shared understanding of the police practices and protocols and the legal constraints that are overseeing the functions of the police here chief Mendez was asked to come and speak to council and he will come to talk about use of force training and answer other questions that council has we many conversations in the past about some of the things that are being requested and I have had the responsibility to be honest that the demands that are being asked for cannot be met through the things that are being requested or demanded from the community because there are systems beyond this these bodies that control what is available in terms of oversight i will also say that the police bureau in contrast to what you may perceive related to bureau right now is very different than when i got here in 2018. there has been a tremendous amount of work done they have put in an amount of effort especially over the last years
led by chief mendez that i'm very proud of and that's why you're taking offense instead of addressing the situation i understand you put in work to change the department yes you fired a few people you did this you did that well there's another issue that has a rise and it needs addressed it doesn't need a constant reminder that you've done things in the past like i said you have to keep taking out the trash the limitations whatever the case may be maybe you do need to have a conversation with your community and fully explain who you put in place here because yous are no longer in place apparently miss lois in order to be fair i'm walking off
thank you good evening i'm heidi shirk 100 block of east lemon street i have two very boring questions um what happened to item b on the agenda did we miss that thank you
that was administration number bill uh sorry bill 2 2025 i mentioned at the top of the meeting that that was going to be removed from the agenda i missed that okay and then my my second sorry
question or comment is earlier during the the first public comment it seemed apparent that there's a time when the person at the podium asks questions or makes a statement and maybe at the closure of their statement is when you respond but it didn't it didn't seem like that was explained to the person at the podium so I was just wondering if that's something in the future either mr. Arroyo whoever's in that seat or mr. Harris can just explain like we will not respond to you and your questions until you finish your comment so just a
little note on that thank you thank you I'm Jenny Calabrese 500 block of North Street my comment is specifically for mayor Sirachi I think it's deeply embarrassing to be a grown woman who took an elected position and sits on this board and smirks at the people who are coming to you with valid concerns you are sitting there and you are defending the police and you're saying we have come so far from 2018 that's probably true I don't know the specifics that's probably true we also abolished slavery which used to be a system that was held up by the law and abolished that do you want a cookie for it doing a cookie for doing the right thing for the people of this community and black and around people and talking to your constituents in such a condescending way, it is not hard to take one step back and have some humility and recognize that, OK, there might be systems in place. But number one, skirting around them does not make the public feel safety or trust in you as an elected official. And number two, systems can change. You can advocate for them. Look at Philly. Look at what Philly just did. I don't remember the name of the organization. It's like CPOC. But their police review board, whatever that's called, they took steps just in January to change how they work with the public to defend people because the systems in place before were not working. So I truly, truly hope that you feel proud of the work that you have done because you have done good work, but you have a long way to go. And I truly hope that the next person who takes your place has a little bit more humility and doesn't smirk at the people who come before them with concerns about teenagers who were brutalized at the hands of the police, which is not the first time this has happened in Lancaster, and we have not made progress since 2018, 2019, 2020. Thank you.
Good evening. My name is Oakley Boscorino. I have to apologize for the deviation of topic, but I'm coming here representing Pennsylvania College of Art and Design and their entire over 400 student body. What excited many students about enrolling in this Lancaster-based art school the artistic world that surrounded it and the creative life that flourishes in this city however a rise of tariffs and general pricing has made businesses shy away from reaching out to artists in suit the rise of artificial intelligence due to its cheapness and accessibility diminishes lancaster's creative vision and neglects opportunities for pcat's population as students working tooth and nail towards success we came here to remind you that pcat is your creative pantry there are over 400 unique artists that are seeking the chance to get get their hands on client-based work and as our careers are being threatened we wish to become more an option for creative businesses and branding needs I'm gonna take time to circle back to AI the very tool that has taken jobs from over 26% of illustrators internationally according to the Society of Authors 43 percent of artists seeing a decrease in their income because of it the International Monetary Fund also claimed that 40% of jobs aside from the art field are actively occupied by artificial intelligence although with this intent to amplify productivity it has actively proven to cause significant job displacement these statistics are exemplified in journal in the Journal of the market for example which is facing nasty competition with chat GBT the famous AI writing assistant that almost half of college students nationwide abused for their assignments and coursework one in five students in America use chat GBT to write essays according to the Pew Research Center 70% of students nationally use it to facilitate research with this tool growing to take up the forefront of education and industry the journalism market has faced lower wages and minimal job opportunities while AI produces work that lacks human understanding Lancaster's community of being a visual arts and small business emporium is also at risk of similar happenings it may be cheaper for business owners to generate AI artwork, but you take away the human touch that your branding designs and illustrations need. On top of that, you strip a job, freelance, or internship opportunity from a selection of over 400 growing artists right here in Lancaster currently attending PCAD. Students who are paying over $100,000 to deem themselves qualified to make that work for you. Other job markets will crumble following the arts if AI isn't rejected. all of this to say this is a cry for help a plea from student creatives who are preparing to step foot into these attack industries Lancaster's unique uniqueness has been excuse me has been created by the hands of creatives for years there are students here eager to utilize their creativity for you for free and as a city that encourages such entrepreneurial ideas we ask that you seek out our passionate students for your design needs Lancaster is human art and as a resident of Lancaster, we ask you how this mission drives. Thank you for your time.
Daryl Legacy, 100 block of North Mary. I'm sure that the finance people were probably not looking forward to this today, but this one speaks to you at least a little. We're lucky that Moody's, when they raided us, didn't take into account the fact that if the police keep acting with impunity, we're going to have multi-million dollar lawsuits that our city is going to be paying, and we're going to deserve it, all right? So far, we've been lucky that they are mostly brutalizing poor people and brown people. Someday they're going to get a rich kid. They're going to get someone that knows a really good lawyer, or there's going to be a lawyer that says this is a slam-dunk case, and we're going to be paying millions, tens of millions of dollars to people because of the police. So if you don't care about any of these other things, I realize there's things you cannot do. You can call them out. Instead of standing with them at their press conference, you can say, no, I will not stand with you. I do not agree with you. Maybe I can't fire you, but I wish I could. And I think even if you just care about the money part, this is a serious problem that we are not solving. We're not even trying to solve it. And I just find myself flabbergasted by the fact that we cannot even do the simplest thing like a review board. Like that is the bare minimum. And so I really, really ask the city council to please put that
the agenda for the next meeting thank you taylor raymond 500 block of st joseph street so it's my understanding that the reason the body cam footage uh isn't being released is because there were minors involved um and their privacy needs to be protected i understand that i don't want to know the identities of people that have gone through something like that something that can be done is you can blur the faces of people and that will help protect their identity um and will uh satisfy part of the demands that have been made for uh for the footage to be released to us additionally uh this is a separate thing um the uh last meeting that i was at it was mentioned that there had been lead pipes um was that for the entirety of lancaster city uh i can answer
your question if you can want to wrap up your comments okay um if it is for the entirety of
the city i never received it in the southwest and neither did any of the people living in my apartment building um and i just need to know why that is that's all absolutely um you should have
received notice of your utility bill or your water bill the city is currently undergoing a lead pipe inventory to see where there potentially are lead pipes throughout the city but you should have received that if not talk to you offline where you can find more information about that I believe that in the case of
renter um he went to both the landlord and the renters yes okay and uh this and also if you can
just confirm with me your address later i will make sure that you follow up um and i just wanted to say that um we are talking about there's 50 000 lines we have to have two forms of verification for the state for those lines right now we have identified about one percent of the lines we are much more concerned in the city of Lancaster related to lead paint than we are to lead pipes but this is a federal mandate this is part of some of the costs that you heard about related to water just a little bit ago and so having to follow up and apartment buildings are a little more complicated but you only have one meter coming in and if we've already identified it we're not following up with all the renters thank you for that
clarification thank you Brian Nelson right off of Columbia Avenue Banyan Circle Drive so I understand that we talked a lot about the failures of our police department and the failures of the mayor on terms of holding them accountable but I wanted to ask a question for each and every single one of you sitting there right now with ICE going through communities deporting individuals who are not even undocumented you know they were deported because of their tattoos some were even American born here and then you also have the Trump administration just going through and cutting federal funding for multiple programs throughout the country that you know provide necessary food and housing for people who lack the resources to do so I want hear from each and every single one of you what your commitment is over the next four years to do something about this and what you guys plan to do in that position that you hold so dearly what are you going to do to make sure that Lancaster remains safe it remains a bastion for those who come here to work and pay taxes and live just according to their values so what is your commitment
that right now. If I may, Vice President, I'd like to answer that question.
Councilor Diaz, just to wrap up a public comment, can you hold your comments until council
comments later? Thank you. Next speaker please. Hi, Sylveta Rosa, Lancaster Township. I just had a question I guess for the mayor and the other councillors if they would like to answer. What is in your power in terms of this policing and what we're talking about what is in your power what are you able to do in terms of mayor sirachi I've seen you the past couple of years address the public I've even seen you cry in public about the policing and how much it's affected you but in terms again of your advocacy for your constituents how does that translate over because then when you do a public press conference aligning yourself with the police it doesn't really align my trust or transparency to want to work with you i know your term is ending so i'm sure you don't really care about us that much but at least that's how it feels um and i did say lancaster township but the water the sewer the police they all operate within the township am i correct in saying that no so you have our own police department okay so the lancaster city police didn't come through my neighborhood then and that's not them going around okay thank you next speaker please
uh john tell tolan first and only block of wise ave um mayor sirachi uh your response to jess lopez was kind of vague and i think that most people here would like to know what the actual limitations are and if there's some kind of town hall we could have so that we could actually go through what the proper channels could be to have some kind of actual action happen when it comes to maybe the desk duty or what we would need to do in order to put pressure on the police department to fire specific police officers or why can't we do that like you're being very vague and i think giving us more detail would kind of help hi um my name is taylor i
taylor enterline i live in manheim borough but i work here in the city and have been put through uh the legal system here um mayor sirachi you're staying on your mayoral time here in lancaster will be remembered and laughed at you stood in 2020 in the streets got your photos and it did nothing the police lied to us then and you they lied to you and then you lied to us and during that time so what are they hiding now and who are we protecting we stood here two weeks ago and every council member stood with the community and said it was disturbing and disgusting what we witnessed and we all waited patiently while you were on vacation which you're allowed to do I all implied implore us to do that but then when you got back we were expecting or hoping that maybe you would denounce the actions that you also witnessed in those videos but no you You stood and did the most disgusting move by blaming the community, families and the children involved and are we willing to accept this type of policing for our children for the crime of no bike reflectors and lights and pulling fire alarms? And now you sit here and dismiss us when we are making demands and trying to rebuild the trust in the community to have transparency and accountability, which everyone seems to want for us and to continue to work together but then it's like just shot down and it doesn't seem like you're willing to do that with us um and that's just really like this state like it's just it just sits with me at the same time we are going to continue to put children who were riding bikes through the legal system to make like to make a stance um and continue forward with this and And I think as we see when the city wants to make an example of someone, they will do so.
Thank you.
Any additional public comment?
And I just want to say for the end, lead paint is the job of housing. Lead pipes are the job of the city. If you would face, if you would focus on the area, because it was already known before, Deneen, you took office that the sewer plant was compromised. 30 years ago, we were in our last 10 years, the solutions were well overdue, but your concern was more about equitable solutions with long-term effects. Officer Hatfield has multiple encounters since 1989 okay his excessive force for decades has many people in this city frightened and with this incident that happened on these young children because they were children 14 15 they're children it's unacceptable it should be condemned this officer should not be on the force he has no self-control it is clearly evident on that video that his training I don't understand how you can pat him on the back and say turn it around and look at these children and say you're the blame it's unacceptable your ignorance to us as taxpayers I mean it's gonna go down in centuries as to who you are but again you're gonna be the president of the home rule so you're already positioned
yeah sucks. Next speaker please. Hello my name is Betty Jones South End Concerned Neighbors. My address is 222 South End. I'm calling I mean I'm here to talk about the issue with trash. Okay on 211 I mean our block I should I mean our area from the 100 block down to the 400 block we received citations for trash that was blown it's not something that we did mother nature through the trash and all of a sudden I call I got a citation so I call and the person that I spoke we told me they got a phone call from someone talking about the trash in the debris so all of everyone from the 100 block to the 400 block got a $25 citation first I called them and I told them I went outside and I'm like okay what's trash I picked up there was a piece of box I have a tree in front of my house so there was tree brick the limbs and everything was on it on the ground plus our property at 259 South and Street okay they came and they cleaned it up we have pictures to show that we went by there today and there's trash boxes and everything out there again okay so I along with everyone else we have the $25 plus the $200 fine I told the lady I'm not paying it i'm gonna fight it because it's not something that i did i went outside and i seen whatever that was there i picked it up i'm sorry if you look at happening at the moment if you don't mind okay she have the pictures she have the pictures to show you because i was talking to them talking i wanted you to see that's the reason why she's there okay so um i just wanted to um talk about that because i don't usually get up and say something but with something they're charging me want to charge me 200 for a cleanup and if you look at the pictures you'll see that what they picked up wasn't nothing it was branches that fell off my tree the city would not give me permission to cut the tree down so therefore the branches are falling down and when they're little branches they're not big big stuff and i i just don't see what they she called she told me that they came and um someone cleaned something up for picking up a box or whatever you're going to charge me 200 for that i mean i could have picked that up myself which i didn't even see anything but if you guys look at the pictures you'll see there wasn't nothing like that that and I did call I did call down and I talked to the person the lady today and I told her that we were going to fight it
thank you
mrs jones i'm meeting with uh director campbell tomorrow and i i know that miss bird had also followed up and i thought that um we had gotten some more information but i will confirm
tomorrow and I'll be in touch. I took pictures that way you can see it. I wasn't, you know, I'm not trying to hide anything or whatever. I took pictures so they can see what was what. You know, if it was a lot of trash or something like that, I can see it. But you're going to charge me $200 for maybe picking up something that came from the 100 block or someplace else? You're going to charge me $225? No, that's not right. And it's not just me. It's everybody. 19 people on block that's what the lady told me she said 19 people got a citation that means from 100 blocks or whatever block it is came blowing from wherever and we all got a fine for $225 no that's not right thank you
again meeting with director Campbell tomorrow morning and I will talk to him about this i understood you brought these um concerns previously yes and um i again i will
make sure that someone and i appreciate that yes and i want to thank uh councilwoman diaz and councilman lechard for responding to the email that i had asked we also asked about a report for stop signs we haven't i guess that's coming too
That is, and so I'm sorry I sent your email to the wrong, an email address that you don't use as frequently, but now I know, and we'll get you that information as well.
Thank you. The other thing I wanted to talk about was that zoning ordinance that got tabled. is there an opportunity that the proposal could be placed on either the city website or a way that we can get a copy of that to see what is being proposed prior to you know it come in before
council yeah that was actually introduced during the commanding community planning committee uh during the last committee session okay that was the uh excuse me blanks direct and price elementary
uh rezoning and that that was taken oh so it was for about the price i did see that i didn't know that's what this was in reference to that was introduced during the last community planning
this was supposed to be the scheduled first reading but that was uh removed from the agenda
all right thank you thank you miss burton jessica lopez completely off topic but um um who's responsible for the removal of no parking signs and handicap signs when the people
who asked for them no longer reside there that's traffic commission and if you send mr harris a note um he can communicate with the staff at the police bureau to send someone out to to confirm that that person no longer lives there and department of public works goes out and removes
the sign or if it's like zoning so say they put no parking signs where there used to be a garage and now said garage is a house do they they receive remove the sign right if said garage doesn't have vehicles going in and out of it i live on a block that has street cleaning every week and about four handicapped spots and no parking on one side so it's like we need every space that we can get on manor street so who reassesses when the zoning is up because i can't walk up and down manor and figure out every spot that should be fixed who does that again it's my
understanding that that is the purview of traffic commission and i would send if you have specific spots with an address like if you can send a house number where there is a handicapped space in front uh i also just say that um that we do have a process of confirming that and so that that's
what traffic commission does so um i mean just for future like i appreciate the response and information but shouldn't there be like um yearly five yearly review when we're literally being incarcerated for not paying these parking tickets for places that
shouldn't be we do and we do have where where you send in the information for Campbell to look at and then we basically review it completely but we have to initiate the process you would have to come also to the meeting so like
that you could bring it forward no but what I'm what I'm saying is shouldn't
there be something established where they do it without us initiating it
because we're busy working for y'all tax money or like if somebody rezones a
property and they're like oh we want to change this garage into a house since a light go off and like ding ding ding is there no parking sign should we remove them that's what I'm saying like when it comes to accountability and transparency of the people who are in place to actually do the job it's not on me to do the job I don't I live in one house that that's the thing like yeah I'm gonna do it for this one but it's like who's gonna do it for the other 12 houses on block and the other 50 60 90 100 blocks in the city people are literally paying out their ass for everything around here at this point we should have somebody who's like you know what let's be smart and not piss people off and just remove these signs miss lopez if you want to just send
me the the addresses i can look into that for you thank you so much have a great rest thank you john
mine is strasburg pennsylvania um i just want to leave you all with um one last message tonight um i think it's really pertinent it's really important um there are a whole lot of people in this room in this city in this greater community that i care for very deeply and within the last month here um talking from everybody from the city and the county um i find that we again have come back here to a city council meeting united on a common front now two weeks ago we were united that we were kind of shocked disturbed and terrified by the video how we saw it right that was the common theme now we don't we know what happened after that i'm not here to relitigate that but as i listen to all of you on that side of the things in the community here what i'm hearing is that this community is afraid of the lancaster city police department. That is really not up for discussion. And it looks differently, right? The community behind me is addressing their fear because they feel that there is over-policing going on. I sense a fear from council and the mayor, that's me just talking out loud, because policing at a national and state and local level has just had its reckoning over the last five years. George Floyd wasn't in the vacuum. These are things that we all have been facing and looking at over the years, and it would be disingenuous for any elected official to act like there's not a policing issue in America. Lancaster has that same problem, and I see that there is a collective fear or anxiety, and it's for different reasons. I understand that. It's for different reasons, but we are still united in that fear, and within that, we need to negotiate on how to come together. Lancaster City needs its own truth and reconciliation. We need a moment where we come together like we have been and not just look at this as a system that cannot be changed. Think about it like this. The 13th Amendment didn't just happen because somebody said, oh we're cool freeing the slaves. Like no, it was a fight. Apartheid didn't just end because Nelson Mandela snapped his finger that's not how it happened we can't accept the status quo because the status quo is unacceptable and you guys know that because you guys have done work over the last five years even though there's not been a lot of credit thrown your way right i see that and there's credit to be given to all of you but right now that credit's not going to be given but i see the work you try to do i acknowledge that the working group was a step in the direction i acknowledge all of you coming down to the protest in 2020 and 21. I acknowledge all that. I know that you guys don't want a bad city with bad police. I know that on my court, but the actions don't, the actions don't reflect the words all the time. And that's where you're seeing the passion being directed towards you all. So I believe that you guys want to do, I believe that you think that you want to do the right thing here. And what I think is there is unity in the disturbance of this issue we're still disturbed and i believe there's unity and that there is a fear of the police force and how they may react if city council does something or how they may react with how the mayor says something or interprets something there's a union i get it i i know you guys are humans too i just want you to take that message and let you know that i see you but we need to get past it we need to come together and have our own truth and reconciliation and unite around that
fear and actually tangibly do something I thank you I live on Spruce Street the 500 block so I just came up here to also address the police brutality incident and the public's concern I can't get the voice out of my head like call my mom call my mom I can't believe that I had to hold my breath while I was watching that video the whole time not knowing completely expecting that that video would get worse like so much we've seen in the news in the media here in our home our hometown I completely believe that I had to hold my breath because I didn't trust what I was watching I didn't trust the Lancaster City Police with an innocent life in their hand and a child at that and why should that be our reality when there are plenty of tax dollars we put into police and the de-escalation and the training the presence of protection and public safety is not lost upon us but deranged beyond measure twisted into a tool that feels more like a knife that's being sharpened into our backs these are our own people especially our bracken black and brown people in the community we need you to show up and show us that you care the excessive use of force is unacceptable the lack of security for my friends our family members the community here I hold my breath again because if the police aren't here for us then who are they who are they here for I think you've been really vague tonight and dancing around your responses especially you mayor in language that doesn't even touch on the subjects you've given us an unclear image of what the systems are in place but please we're not stupid help us under and understand empower us you've been vague and uninterested just disingenuine interacting with your community members and the needs but you're who we elected to take care of us and we've been clear you've been vague and we've been clear so what are you going to do so we're asking again for accountability for the officers involved public recognition of your shortcomings not just your excuses and to let you know we're afraid don't you care help us so thank you
Hi, my name is Brianna Sienkiewicz. I'm on the 700 block of Marietta Avenue. This is my first time speaking up here, but I moved here in 2022. I moved here because I wanted this to be a safe community for my son. My husband is Haitian, so my son is mixed. I always watched that video and all I could see was my son on the ground and it made me sob I expect that living here we are safe but it makes me wonder because my son is not white and he is never going to be seen as that that could easily be him in 13 years we're already facing a constitutional crisis in our federal government people are already scared we don't need to be scared in our local communities where we actually hold the power so that's why I'm up here because I can't remain quiet I hope in 13 years I don't have to be standing here speaking about this thank you any additional public comment with
that we'll move on to the report of the mayor mayor sir okay I'm going to talk
about a few of the things that have been addressed so far this evening council received a report related to our tree program and there was a question about a one million dollar america for american forest grant through the u.s forest service to help bolster our street tree program in our neighborhoods um as you know a number of our federal grants have been in question and we've been working through uh that as best as possible i'm pleased to let council know tonight that this grant is moving forward uh and uh we will be uh working in our neighborhoods uh collectively to add more street trees uh neighbors can submit their own um have their own street tree planted right now and there is more information about this about this program at the city of lancaster pa.gov forward slash planting uh i know that tina i'm sorry director campbell uh has already mentioned the good news related to our bond reading as being moved from an a3 stable to a3 positive uh as she mentioned this not only lowers our bond interest rates but affects other things that are always considered related to future insurance premiums and the like um so i i just want to also thank director campbell who has been in her position um just over a year 18 months and has been working diligently to continue to move this the city forward with the home rule a study commission and the increased financial reporting especially as it relates to our capital plan all of those things are moving forward uh you will be receiving your first quarterly financial brief um in april uh and we'd be receiving monthly reports moving forward as well as those quarterly financial reports and i'm underscoring this for commissioner a former commissioner miss bird who i know that that was something that was important to you and it's important just in general the other thing I want to let everybody know is that we are continuing our quarterly testing of PFAS in our water system and our recent testing still has a running annual average above the DEP mandated limit for PFOA in water source from the Conestoga River Lancaster County and much of the state continues to be under a drought watch which is a major contributor to these higher results and so just you know remember running averages if it is higher for a couple of quarters that running average stays with us until we have several quarters of lower averages the way that we get lower averages is if it rains and there's more water in the river I wanted to make sure that for council's awareness that each time we go above the mandated running average we must send out a letter to all customers and i believe that those letters cost about twenty five thousand dollars each time we send a letter which we are required to do and so we will be spending another twenty five thousand dollars in the next few weeks to alert residents to this fact we continue to monitor this issue explore solutions and additional information about our pfas and our testing results are posted on the city of lancasterpa.gov i also put in the caveat always that drinking water represents about 20 of your exposure to pfos and that drinking bottled water is uh not as safe does not need to have to meet the same drinking water quality standards as water that is produced by the city and so i just caveat that because buying bottled water is not going to avoid pfos and that concludes my report
tonight. Thank you, Mayor Sirachi. We'll move on to the reporter president of council. Council president did not have a report for this evening. Moving on to council comments. I'll open it up
for council to speak. Councilor Diaz. I just wanted to address the gentleman in regards to the immigration. I'm currently volunteering some hours being that I am bilingual and have the opportunities to do intakes. If anyone is interested, there's a parish. It's called Parish Resource Center. It's at 2160 Lincoln Highway East. And if you know anyone that needs the resources or the help, there will be attorneys after the intake that will speak to them. Thank you. That's all I have.
Thank you, Councilor Diaz. Any additional Council comments? Councilor Cleese?
Thank you, Consul President. In terms of immigration, legal immigration, as a Consul member, there isn't much we can do. Let's be honest. So what I can do, I can use my voice, my platform, my vote. I can speak out, and I have done that. You know, you use newspaper, everybody needs to speak out. And we can see that now many people are silent. They don't speak out because they are afraid and i want to let you know that i support the call of the community i support the community's call for greater transparency and i encourage the police department to publicly release all past use of force and including the latest use of force reports ensuring residents have access to important public safety information open communication is essential to building trust and accountability i am deeply concerned about the incident and the response provided in the press in the recent western friends Our community deserves full transparency and accountability in such matters. Our community deserves a commitment to just and equitable policing. Public safety is essential to any community. It's fundamental. But it's a collaboration between local government, police, and the community. Clearly that collaboration is broken. I'm in favor of any measures, any measures that can help repair it, up to and including a civil review board. It's necessary to engage in an open and transparent discussion between community members, city officials, and our enforcement to bring choices back to the community. That's my comment for tonight.
Thank you, Mr. Vice President, and I just want to react to the remarks of the gentleman about the immigration. There is a lot of effort going on at the state level with different organizations here in Lancaster that I am a part of, and I would love to connect with you and talk about some of the acts you are doing at the state level.
Thank you. Any additional council comments? With that, I'll just end.
One, I want to thank the community for showing up tonight, similar to the last council meeting.
During the last council meeting, I mentioned that you guys are being heard, and I want to continue to echo that sentiment. I understand that the press conference that was recently given that answer
everyone's questions one of the things that I what I'm hearing from the
community is that there is broken trust I think one of the things that we've learned from decades of you know public safety efforts is that there's a loss of trust there and as much as we've done to rebuild it to miss Lopez's point there is uh we must maintain it and uh i want to make sure that we continue to do so there are a couple initiatives that are underway one of the things that i'm committed to doing is making sure that data continues to be transparent and where it's not transparent where can we show more historical data so that way we can see some of the progress that we have made um i want you guys to hear from me uh this is not picking sides the one thing i do want to emphasize that no progress is made in separation this will take both the community the police department city hall and whatever new administration walks into this building in 2026 it requires unity can be done through separation so with that i think there's opportunity for more community engagement whether that's awareness on progress whether that's educational process or how can we do better and i think there's always opportunities for improvement on both sides. And you can be empathetic and hold people accountable. And I will say that goes for both sides. Our community, our police department, we can hold each other accountable. We can also be empathetic in the process. So I know that doesn't answer anything to Mr. Miner's point. This stuff can't happen with the snap of a finger. Culture eats strategy for breakfast. And it's important that we make sure that we continue to build a culture and a community where everyone feels safe and that will take time but continue your advocacy continue to speak to your council members your mayor your police officers building trust starts with conversation and I appreciate you guys coming here to start that thank you with no further council comments I'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn second we have a motion and a second all those in favor aye meeting adjourned
Okay, I'm going to call one of us. I don't know if that works. I don't know if that works. I don't know if that works. Thanks for coming.